<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<title>Rodrigo Luger's Blog</title>
<link>https://luger.dev/blog</link>
<description>A blog about astronomy, data science, math, and random thoughts that pop into my head.</description>
<atom:link href="https://luger.dev/blog/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

<item>
<title>Normalized GPs</title>
<link>https://luger.dev/blog/2021-01-04.html</link>
<guid>https://luger.dev/blog/2021-01-04.html</guid>
<pubDate>Mon, 4 Jan 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>I ran into an interesting statistics problem while working on my interpretable Gaussian process for stellar light curves (see <a href='2020-10-01.html'>this post</a>). What happens to the covariance structure of a dataset when we normalize it to its own mean (or median)? This is something that happens a lot in the literature: astronomers love normalizing light curves to sweep the unknown baseline under the rug and convert their data in relative units. But it turns out that this is a dangerous thing to do, especially if you then go on to model it with a Gaussian process! In this post I'll show an example of this, how it can bias GP inference (in particular for periodic datasets), and how to fix it.</description>
</item>

<item>
<title>Interpretable GPs for stellar rotation (Part 3)</title>
<link>https://luger.dev/blog/2021-01-03.html</link>
<guid>https://luger.dev/blog/2021-01-03.html</guid>
<pubDate>Sun, 3 Jan 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>This is a (long overdue) continuation of a <a href='2020-10-01.html'>previous post</a>, in which I discussed the development of an interpretable Gaussian process for stellar light curves. This post is mainly a wrapper for a talk I gave a couple months ago on the topic, so if you have 20 minutes (and an interest in stellar light curve modeling), please check it out!</description>
</item>

<item>
<title>Synthetic Likelihoods</title>
<link>https://luger.dev/blog/2020-10-27.html</link>
<guid>https://luger.dev/blog/2020-10-27.html</guid>
<pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>In this post I dig a little deeper into the assumptions I'm making when I try to model stellar surfaces (and, equivalently, stellar light curves) using a Gaussian Process. The true likelihood function for the data is certainly not a gaussian, but it turns out that approximating it as such is not a terrible idea. Here I'll discuss the concept of a synthetic likelihood, which is a term from the ecology literature (and is probably called different things in different fields), and explore its behavior with a very simple toy model. I'll warn you right now that I'm in a bit over my head with this, so comments / thoughts from proper statisticians are most welcome!</description>
</item>

<item>
<title>Interpretable GPs for stellar rotation (Part 2)</title>
<link>https://luger.dev/blog/2020-10-01.html</link>
<guid>https://luger.dev/blog/2020-10-01.html</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 1 Oct 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>This is a continuation of the previous post, in which we implemented a very slow, inefficient, and numerically unstable Gaussian process for stellar light curves. In this post I'll discuss how to compute the GP kernel analytically and show how to use this GP to learn about star spot properties from stellar light curves.</description>
</item>

<item>
<title>Interpretable GPs for stellar rotation (Part 1)</title>
<link>https://luger.dev/blog/2020-09-24.html</link>
<guid>https://luger.dev/blog/2020-09-24.html</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>The information content of stellar light curves can be exceptionally tiny, owing to the large number of degeneracies when projecting from a two-dimensional space (the stellar surface) to a one-dimensional curve (the flux timeseries). Instead of trying to produce a definitive map of a stellar surface from a light curve, we can instead model the surface as a statistical process. In this post, I discuss ongoing work to develop a Gaussian process for stellar light curves whose hyperparameters are rooted in statistical properties of the stellar surface.</description>
</item>

<item>
<title>So I started a blog...</title>
<link>https://luger.dev/blog/2020-09-17.html</link>
<guid>https://luger.dev/blog/2020-09-17.html</guid>
<pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
<description>Ever since I started my postdoc at the CCA, it feels like I've started a million different projects (and finished none). I have a lot of half-finished (or more like half-baked) ideas that I felt I had to write down somewhere, so I decided to start a blog! This blog will be a mishmash of posts on astronomy, data science, math, and any other random thoughts that pop into my head.</description>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>